In the same way we use decibels for power ratio.
We're going to use decibels for the power value itself.
The unit is dBm.
When we speak about power in decimal, we use the value compared to one milliwatts, and that's where
the name dBm comes from.
The m stands for
milliwatt.
That means that if we have a power of 1 mW.
What's 1 mW
in relation to
1 mW?
It's equal.
So we have 0 dBm.
If we have two milliwatts. What's 2 mW in comparison to 1 mW?
It's multiplied by two.
So we have 3 dBm, and if we have a multiplication by ten, so ten milliwatts then the power
is 10 dBm and we have exactly the same operation
for values below 1 mW. If we divide by two?
So 0.5 mW we have minus 3 dBm. And if we divide by ten, so 0.1 mW, we have minus
-10 dBm.
So let's take an example.
We'll use the example of the Walkie-Talkie, which has a transmission power of 2 W, and we tried
to find a transmission power in dBm.
For that, we just have to compare this value to 1 mW.
To what is 1 mW
multiplied by ten, ten, ten, which makes 1000 and I multiply it again by two, which gives
2W.
Now what's the value in dBm ? 1 mW is 0 dBm and multiplication by ten gives each time 10 dBm and
the multiplication by two gives 3 dBm.
So the transmission power of the Walkie-Talkie is therefore 33 dBm. Now that we've understood how decibels
work.
We can study a LoRa transmission and verify if the values representing this transmission are interesting
for long range.
That's what we're going to do in the next video.